在这个小节,我想告诉你另一个密钥交换方法基于
In this module I wanna show you another
approach to key exchange based on the
公钥加密的概念 我要再一次提醒你们的那个系统 我们
concept of public key encryption. So again
just to remind you of the system, we
一如既往 我们的好朋友爱丽丝和鲍勃 他们彼此交换密钥K
have our friends Alice and Bob as usual,
and they're both to exchange a secret key
窃听者可以看到他们发送给对方的消息 但是
K. The eavesdropper gets to see the
messages they send to one another, but
尽管他不知道关于密钥K的任何信息
even though he shouldn't learn anything
about the key K that, that they exchanged.
和往常一样 在这个小节 我们来看窃听安全性
And as usual in this module we're only
going to be looking at eavesdropping
这里我们不允许攻击者篡改数据或其他
security. That is we don't allow the
attacker to tamper with data or to mount
任何形式的主动攻击 所以仅仅提醒你们 这个小节的开头我们
any other form of active attack. So, just
to remind you, earlier in this module we
来看一个基于通用分组密码的低效率的机制 在之前的部分
saw an inefficient mechanism based on
generic block ciphers. In the previous
我们学习了Diffie-Hellman密钥交换机制
segment we saw the Diffie-Hellman key
exchange mechanism which has an
这是一个参与者与攻击者所要做的工作有指数差距的机制
exponential gap between the work that the
participants have to do versus the work
事实上这个Diffie-Hellman协议
that the attacker has to do. And in fact
this Diffie-Hellman protocol is used all
在网页上用的很频繁 这节课我要给你们讲一种
over the web very frequently. In this
segment I want to show you, a different
基于公开密钥加密的不同的方法 那什么是公开加密？ 就像
approach based on public key encryption.
So, what is public encryption? So just as
在对称加密的情况下 这是对称加密的加密算法
in the case of symmetric encryption
there's an encryption algorithm and a
和解密算法 然而这里的加密算法给定了一个密钥
decryption algorithm. However, here the
encryption algorithm is given one key,
就是我们所谓的公开密钥 我们称它为鲍勃的
which we're going to call a public key.
Let's call this the public key that
公钥 解密算法给定了另外的密钥
belongs to Bob. And the decryption algorithm is given a different key, we'll
我们称之为私钥 它也是鲍勃的 这两个密钥有时
call it a secret key. That also belongs to
Bob. So these two keys are sometimes
被合称为密钥对 密钥对的一半是公钥 另一半是
called a key pair. One half of the pair is
the public key and the other half of the
私钥 现在你们的加密方式跟往常一样 一个消息
pair is the secret key. Now the way you
encrypt this as usual, a message would
进来 加密算法会生成一个密文 这是
come in, the encryption algorithm would
generate a cipher text, that is the
用公钥加密的消息 当这个密文
encryption of this message using the given
public key. And then when the cipher text
被送到解密算法那里 解密算法会输出
is given to the decryption algorithm, the
decryption algorithm basically outputs the
相应的消息 如我所说 PK是公钥 SK是
corresponding message. So, as I said, PK
is called the public key and SK is called
私钥 更准确地说 什么是公开加密  公开加密
the secret key. So more precisely, what is
public encryption? Well, public encryption
通常由三个算法组成 G E和D 算法G是被称为
is actually made up of three algorithms,
G, E, and D. Algorithm G is what's called
密钥生成算法 当你运行算法G的时候 它会输出两个密钥
a key generation algorithm. When you run
algorithm G, it will output two keys, the
公钥和私钥 加密算法的消息中
public key and the secret key. The
encryption algorithm basically, given the
给出公钥 就会输出相应的密文
public key in the message, will output the
corresponding cipher text. And the
解密算法的密文中给出私钥 就会
decryption algorithm, given the secret key
in the cipher text, will output the
输出原文 如果发生错误 它将停止输出 像往常一样
message or it will output bottom if an
error occurred. And as usual we have the
和我们通常的一致性属性说 对于任何密钥生成算法
usual consistency properties that say that
for any public key and secret key that
输出的公钥和私钥 如果我们使用的公钥加密消息
could have been output by the key generation
algorithm if we encrypt the message using
然后使用私钥解密 我们就能够得到
the public key and then decrypt using the
secret key we should get the original
原始消息 现在 这意味着公钥系统是安全的？
message back. Now, what does it mean for a
public key system to be secure? Well, we
我们用之前使用过的语义安全的概念 除了这个游戏
use the same concept of semantic security
that we used before, except the game is now
现在有点难 我来解释一下 我们该如何定义语义
a little bit different. So let me
explain, how we define semantic security
公钥系统的安全 这里 挑战者会运行这个密钥 生成
for a public key system. So here, the
challenger is gonna run the key generation
算法生成一个公钥和一个私钥对 他要把这个
algorithm to generate a public key and a
secret key pair, and he's gonna give the
公钥给对手 挑战者自己保留私钥
public key to the adversary. The
challenger keeps the secret key to
对手要做的是 他会像之前一样输出两个等长的消息M0和
himself. What the adversary will do is he
will output two equal length messages M0 and
M1 然后这个挑战者会给他M0和M1的密文
M1 as before and then the challenger will
give him the encryption of M0 or M1. As
像往常一样 我们定义两个试验：试验0和试验1 试验0中
usual we define two experiments: experiment
zero and experiment one. In experiment
对手已知M0的密文 试验1中对手
zero the adversary is given the encryption
of M0. In experiment one the adversary is
已知M1的密文 然后对手的目标是猜测
given the encryption of M1 and then the
adversary's goal is to guess which
他已知的是哪个密文 是M0的密文还是
encryption he was given. Was he given the
encryption of M0 or was he given
M1的密文呢 我们指的是他猜测输出是试验0
encryption of M1. And we refer to his
guess as the output of experiment zero or
还是试验1 有一件事我要强调 对于公共
experiment one. One thing I want to
emphasize is that in the case of public
加密 没必要给攻击者太多选择明文加密
encryption there's no need to give the
attacker the ability to mount a chosen
攻击的能力 为什么呢？在一个对称密钥系统中
plaintext attack. Why is that? Well in
the case of a symmetric key system, the
攻击者必须先请求他所选择的消息的密文 在对称
attacker had to request the encryption of
messages of his choice. In the case of a
密钥系统中 攻击者拥有公钥 因此他可以自己
public key system, the attacker has the
public key and therefore he can by
为自己加密任何他想要的消息 他不需要
himself, encrypt for himself any message
that he wants. He doesn't need the
挑战者帮助去产生他所选择的消息的密文 因此
challenger's help to create encryptions of
messages of his choice. And as a result,
在公钥系统中 选择密文攻击是固有的 我们没有理由
in a public key system, a chosen
plaintext attack is inherent. There's no
给攻击者额外的力量去增加这一个选择密文攻击
reason to give the attacker extra power to
mount a chosen plaintexts attack. And
这就是我们我们从不讨论选择明文查询的上下文中
that's why we never discussed chosen
plaintext queries in the context of
定义的语义查询公钥系统的安全的原因 我们定义的
defining semantic security for public key
systems. Now that we defined the game
那个游戏 我们会说,一个公钥系统GED基本上
we're going to say that a public key system
GED is semantically secure if
是语义安全 如果攻击者无法区分试验0和试验1
basically the attacker cannot distinguish
experiment zero from experiment one. In
换句话说 对手在试验0输出1的概率和
other words, the adversary's probability
of outputting one in experiment zero is
他在试验1输出1的概率相同
about the same as his probability of
outputting one in experiment one. So again,
所以 攻击者不能确定他是已知M0的密文
the attacker can't tell whether he was
given the encryption of M0 or the
还是M1的密文 现在我们理解了什么是公钥加密
encryption of M1. Now that we understand
what a public key encryption is let's see
我们来看如何使用它来建立一个共享的秘密 这是我们的朋友爱丽丝和
how to use it to establish a shared
secret. See here are our friends Alice and
鲍勃 爱丽丝将开始通过密钥生成算法给自己
Bob. Alice will start off by generating a
random public key secret key pair for
生成一个随机的公钥密钥对 她要把公钥PK
herself using the key generation
algorithm. And then she's going to send to
发送给鲍勃 她还说 嗨 这个消息是来自爱丽丝的 鲍勃
bob the public key PK. And she also says,
hey this message is from Alice. What Bob
要做的是 他会产生一个128比特的随机数值X 并把这些发送给爱丽丝
will do is he will generate a random 128
bit value X and he will send back to Alice
说 嗨这个消息来自鲍勃 而且他会返回X在爱丽丝的
saying hey this message is from Bob and he
will send back the encryption of X under
公钥加密下的值 爱丽丝会收到这个密文 她会用自己的
Alice's public key. Alice will receive
this cipher text, she will decrypt it
私钥解密 她会得到X的值 现在X的值
using her secret key and that will give
her the value X and now this value X can
可以被当做他们之间的共享秘密 我要强调的是
be used basically as a shared secret
between the two of them. I wanna emphasize
这个协议跟我们在上节课中看到的Diffie-Hellman协议
that this protocol is very different from
the Diffie-Hellman protocol that we saw in
很不一样 这里 当事人必须轮流发送 在某种意义上
the last segment in the sense that here
the parties have to take turns, In the
鲍勃不能发送消息 直到他从爱丽丝接收消息
sense that Bob cannot send his message
until he receives the message from Alice.
换句话说 鲍勃不能用爱丽丝的公钥加密X直到他从爱丽丝那里收到公钥
In other words, Bob cannot encrypt X to
Alice's public key until he receives the
然而在Diffie-Hellman协议中 这两个参与者可以
public key from Alice. In the
Diffie-Hellman protocol however the two
随心所欲的发送消息 完全没有顺序限制
parties could send their messages at
arbitrary times and there was no ordering
这样就有了一个很好的例子关于Diffie-Hellman的应用
enforced on those messages. As a result we
had this nice application of
例如 每个人都可以在FACEBOOK上上传他们的消息
Diffie-Hellman, where, everybody could
post their messages to Facebook, for
我们简单来看下FACEBOOK 任何一对都会有一个共有的密钥
example. And then just by looking at
Facebook profiles, any pair would already
而不需要任何附加的联系
have a shared key, without any need for
additional communication. Here, this is
这里 并不是非常正确 即使每个人都可以把他们的密钥发送给FACEBOOK
not quite true, even if everybody posts
their public key to Facebook, there would
他们也仍旧需要发送一条信息在密钥生成之前。
still be a need to send this message
before a shared key can be established. So
现在 我们理解了这个协议 那么第一个问题来了 为什么这个协议是安全的
now that we understand protocol the first
question we need to ask is why is this
通常我们会仅仅看它的窃听安全性
protocol secure. And as usual we're only
gonna look at eavesdropping security. So
针对这个协议 攻击者会先观察公钥以及用公钥加密的X的密文
in this protocol the attacker gets to see
the public key and the encryption of X
然后 他就会要来求出X的值
under the public key and what he wants to
get is basically this value X. Now we know
现在我们就知道了公钥系统是语义上安全的
that the system the public key system that
we used is semantically secure, what that
这就意味着攻击者不能从随机序列中区分出X
means is that the attacker cannot
distinguish the encryption of X, From the
换句话说 仅仅给出X的密文
encryption of something random. In other
words, just given encryption of X, the
攻击者是不能得知他得到的是X的明文 还是M中一段随机码
attacker can't tell whether the plain text
is X or just some random junk that was
正因为这样 我们可以说 通过观察这个协议中的消息
chosen from M, And because of that, that
basically says that just by looking at
攻击者不能从M的随机元素中区分出X的值
messages in this protocol, the value of X
is indistinguishable in the attacker's
结果就是 X可以被这两个参与者作为会话密钥
view from a random element in M and as a
result, X can be used as a session key
仅仅通过一个随机值 攻击者是不能
between the two parties. It's just a
random value which the attacker cannot
猜测到M中的所有其他可能值的
actually guess other than by trying all
possible values in M. Then I should say
那么 我可以说 从语义安全上来说 这两个分布是不可区分的
that showing that these two distributions
are distinguishable follows directly from
事实上 这有一个简单的练习
semantic security and in fact it's a
simple exercise to show that if the
假如攻击者可以区分这两个分布
attacker could distinguish this
distribution from that distribution then
那他同样可以打破语义安全性 通常来说
the attacker could also break semantic
security. And as usual even though this
即使这个协议面对窃听是安全的 那它针对中间人攻击也是不安全的
protocol is secure against eavesdropping,
it's completely insecure against the
好吧 我们来看个中间人攻击的例子
man-in-the-middle attack. So let's see a
simple man in the middle attack. Well so
爱丽丝生成了她自己的公钥密钥对
here we have Alice generating her public
key secret key pair. At the same time the
同时中间人也生成他的公钥密钥对
man in the middle is also going to
generate his own public key secret key
当爱丽丝把她的公钥发送给鲍勃时 中间人截获了公钥
pair. And now when Alice sends her public
key over to Bob, The man in the middle
然后他用一条消息来替代爱丽丝的公钥
will intercept that and instead he'll say
yeah this is a message from Alice, but
但是因为爱丽丝的公钥是最初的 所以鲍勃收到这条消息
Alice's public key is p K prime. So now
Bob receives this message, he thinks he
他会认为这是一条来自爱丽丝的消息 并且他会选择一个随机数X
got a message from Alice, what he'll send
back is, well he's going to choose his
然后会把最初的PK加密过的X发送回爱丽丝
random X, and he'll send back the
encryption of X under PK prime. The man in
中间人将会截获这条消息 并且他会用别的东西替换它
the middle is going to intercept this
message, and he's going to replace it with
他的目标是确保密钥被成功替换掉
something else. So, his goal is to make
sure that the key exchange succeeds, in
换句话说爱丽丝人认为她收到了一条来自鲍勃的消息
other words Alice thinks that she got a
message from Bob, and yet the man in the
并且中间人也会准确地知道他们所交换的秘密是什么
middle should know exactly what the
exchanged secret is. So what should the man in
那么这种情况下 中间人应该给爱丽丝发送什么呢 我们先称之为密文C
the middle send to Alice in this case? So
yeah let's call the cipher text C. What
中间人会用他自己的密钥来解密密文C
the man in the middle will do is he will
decrypt the cipher text C using his own
这样就会将X暴露在中间人面前 然后
secret key that will reveal X to the man
in the middle. And then he's going to go
他就会直接用爱丽丝的公钥来加密X 并将其发送给爱丽丝
ahead and encrypt X under Alice's public
key, send the value back to Alice. Alice
爱丽丝得到了这个X 并且她以为自己和鲍勃交换了密钥
will obtain this X and as far as she's
concerned, she just did a key exchange
他们两个都得到了X的值 但问题是
with Bob, where both of them learned the
value X, but the problem of course is that
中间人也知道了X的值 所以这个协议是完全不安全的
the man in the middle also knows the value
X. So this protocol becomes completely
一旦中间人篡改了爱丽丝和鲍勃之间的消息的话
insecure once the man in the middle can
tamper with messages from Alice to Bob and
所以我们来做些事情来让这个协议变得安全
from Bob to Alice. So again we have to do something to this protocol to make it secure and
我们要做的是 数字签名
we're gonna see how to do that, actually,
in two weeks after we introduce digital
那么现在 我要告诉你们的就是 公钥加密意味着
signatures. So now that I've show you that
public encryption implies key exchange
面对窃听的密钥交换安全 那我们如何来构建一个公钥加密系统呢
security against eavesdropping. The next
question is how do we construct public key
一般来说 我们需要依靠数字理论和代数
encryption systems? And it turns out that
these constructions generally rely on
就像Diffie-Hellman协议依靠代数构建而成
number theory and some algebra, and just
like the Diffie-Hellman protocol relied on
在我们看这些协议的更多细节之前
some algebra. And so before we go into
these protocols in more detail what I'd
我想简单的绕个弯 说个别的东西 在下一小节中
like to do is kind of take a quick detour.
In the next module we're going to look at
我们要介绍下相关的数字理论的背景 我们会用一个小节介绍它
the relevant number theory background.
We'll just do one module on this and then
然后再回来看公钥设施以及更多密钥交换的例子
come back and talk about these public key
constructions and more constructions for
所以这就是这一小节的结尾了 提前预习下
key exchange. So this is the end of this
module. And as further reading, I just
第一张上面我想在这里指出的是 如果我们依靠对称加密
wanted to point to this paper that shows
if in fact all we do is rely on symmetric
以及Hash函数 那么Merkle谜题就是最好的关于密钥交换
ciphers and hash functions then
Merkle puzzles are optimal for key
并且事实上 我们不可能比一个二次间隙做的更多
exchange and in fact we cannot achieve
more than a quadratic gap as long as we
除非我们先得到原始的黑匣子
treat the primitives we're given as a
black box. So basically this shows that a
所以说 二次间隙是最好的可能
quadratic gap is the best possible and
also I wanted to point to another paper
然后另一张上面总结了我们说过的这些密钥交换机制
that kind of summarizes some of these key
exchange mechanisms that we talked about,
包括了使用公钥加密的密钥交换和使用了Diffie-Hellman的密钥交换
key exchange using public key cryptography
and key exchange using Diffie-Hellman. You
你可以看一下这一页 可以预习下后面的东西
can take a look at this paper and it kind
of will give you a look ahead into what's
也可以明白怎么让密钥交换协议怎么抵御中间人攻击
coming and how to make these key exchange
protocols secure against man in the middle
而不仅仅是面对窃听 好吧 这一小节到这里就结束了
and not just secure against eavesdropping.
Okay so that's the end of this module and
在下一节中 我们会简单的说一下
in the next module we'll take a brief
detour and do a kind of a brief overview
算数和数字理论
of algebra and number theory.